<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rotvie.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rotvie.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-29T21:45:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rotvie.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ricardo Huaman</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">My Journey Learning Japanese</title><link href="https://rotvie.github.io/blog/2025/my-journey-learning-japanese/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Journey Learning Japanese"/><published>2025-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rotvie.github.io/blog/2025/my-journey-learning-japanese</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rotvie.github.io/blog/2025/my-journey-learning-japanese/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="my-childhood">My Childhood</h2> <p>Looking back, I think I’ve always had an interest in languages. The idea of communicating in ways that other people couldn’t easily understand fascinated me. It all started when I was around 8 years old. I remember learning an alternative symbol for each letter of the alphabet and writing secret messages with those. It was quite fun, but it had the shortcoming that I was the only one who knew that code, so I couldn’t share my ideas with others.</p> <p>A few years later, when I was 12, I learned about Braille and finally understood what the symbols on the buttons of elevators meant. But most importantly, I appreciated the cleverness in such a system that allowed blind people to read. During the following years, I realized that learning a new language would be much more useful, so I set that as my goal.</p> <h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started</h2> <p>There were many options. I tried some of them using Duolingo and similar apps. I studied French, Portuguese, German, Italian, Esperanto, among other languages, but of all of them, Japanese was the one that really got my attention. It seemed complex, yet Japanese culture was so widespread that it shouldn’t be too hard, I thought—how naive I was then.</p> <p>In December 2014, I decided that I was going to master Japanese. At first, I started reading a book of common phrases in Japanese with its translation in Spanish. However, that alone wasn’t going to take me far, so I began looking for a concise grammar book. That’s when I came across <a href="https://www.guidetojapanese.org/grammar_guide.pdf"><em>Japanese Grammar Guide</em></a> by Tae Kim.</p> <h2 id="first-attempt">First Attempt</h2> <p>English was a compulsory subject in my school, so I knew the basics, but I was still far from being fluent. Nonetheless, if I wanted to read that Tae Kim textbook, I had to force myself to read English.</p> <p>In 2015, after learning Hiragana with the help of mnemonics, I began reading the book. During that process, I had to look up many English words and sentence structures that now are obvious to me. I think the most noticeable change then was how much my English improved—more than my Japanese, even.</p> <p>Around that time, I also liked to use a website called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lang-8.com">Lang-8</a> where you could post paragraphs in the language you were learning for native speakers to correct. I also bought <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Remembering_the_Kanji"><em>Remembering the Kanji</em></a> by James Heisig, but never really read it because of bad reviews I saw immediately afterwards (I kind of regret not reading it then).</p> <h2 id="getting-off-track">Getting Off Track</h2> <p>I didn’t finish reading <em>Japanese Grammar Guide</em>. I got sidetracked by English content on the internet, but at least I had the general idea of how Japanese worked. A few years passed and my English understanding improved gradually. I knew some Japanese already too, so I thought I would get better if I kept reviewing a little here and there. That never happened.</p> <p>I still had the intention of becoming fluent in another language. Japanese was at the top of my list, but I wasn’t sure how to tackle a language that looked so different from the others. At the end of 2019, Matt vs Japan Youtube channel finally clarified the strategy for me.</p> <h2 id="finding-direction">Finding Direction</h2> <p>The approach to language learning that he used to learn Japanese made sense to me. He said that the most important thing was to focus on getting input in the target language through reading and listening. I reflected upon the way I learned English and everything clicked for me—immersion in the language is crucial.</p> <p>What about Kanji? There are thousands of those Chinese characters. Matt’s solution was the book Remembering the Kanji along with a software for spaced repetition called <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/">Anki</a>.</p> <h2 id="second-attempt">Second Attempt</h2> <p>Once again, I was all-in with Japanese, but this time I had a plan. The first few months of 2020, I was learning to write Kanji at a rate of 25 new characters every day using mnemonics and Anki. When I got to a thousand, I stopped to prioritize watching Japanese content. Maybe I should have continued until I was done with the 2,200 Kanji in the book, but I was excited to start watching actual Japanese and expand my vocabulary.</p> <p>After a couple of months of consuming content in Japanese, I returned to Kanji and finished the book at last.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/my-japanese-handwriting-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/my-japanese-handwriting-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/my-japanese-handwriting-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/my-japanese-handwriting.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>My Kanji handwriting</p> <h2 id="where-im-at">Where I’m At</h2> <p>In July 2022 I passed the <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/ricardo-jesus-huaman-kemper_certificado-jlpt-n2-activity-6988881391144812544-pfup?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAACZjz_wBVCnBVO8PKF0qAZFPBmbqVUDky4I">JLPT N2</a> exam after doing immersion for around 2 years at that point. I’ve also created a <a href="https://github.com/Rotvie/ajatt">repository</a> where I share the tools and resources I’ve found most useful for language learning. Now I’m just keeping the routine of learning new words through a technique called <em>Sentence Mining</em> and trying to immerse myself in the language as much as possible, although it’s been harder lately because of other priorities.</p> <p>I omitted tons of details in my story, mainly because I don’t remember them well or because they’re kind of irrelevant. I wanted to write this down before I forget even further.</p> <h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2> <p>I think learning Japanese has been and continues to be an enriching experience that has shaped who I am now. I encourage everyone who is thinking about learning a new language to give it a try—not just for the sake of a better resume or a job opportunity. Don’t get me wrong, I recognize those are great things too. Just don’t underestimate the impact it can have on one’s understanding of different cultures and perspectives.</p> <p>Best of luck with your studies!</p>]]></content><author><name>Ricardo Huaman</name></author><category term="japanese,"/><category term="language"/><category term="learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My personal journey learning Japanese]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Setting Up and Running microROS on the Raspberry Pi Pico</title><link href="https://rotvie.github.io/blog/2023/uros/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setting Up and Running microROS on the Raspberry Pi Pico"/><published>2023-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rotvie.github.io/blog/2023/uros</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rotvie.github.io/blog/2023/uros/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>In the rapidly evolving world of robotics and embedded systems, microROS is a game-changer. It brings the capabilities of ROS (Robot Operating System) 2 to microcontrollers, facilitating the development of robust and interactive systems. The Raspberry Pi Pico, with its powerful RP2040 chip, provides an excellent platform for such applications.</p> <p>This tutorial will guide you through setting up and running microROS on the Raspberry Pi Pico. By the end of this tutorial, you’ll be equipped to leverage the power of microROS on your Raspberry Pi Pico <d-cite key="RoboFoundry_2022"></d-cite> <d-cite key="ubuntuGettingStarted"></d-cite> <d-cite key="micro-ros-agent-ros"></d-cite> <d-cite key="micro-ros-agent-github"></d-cite>.</p> <p>For the corresponding <strong>YouTube tutorial</strong>, click <a href="https://youtu.be/_4aLzvG6dfw?si=oyEmNZsfEt8569Nv">here</a>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="setting-up-the-environment">Setting up the Environment</h2> <p>Install the necessary dependencies with the following command:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>apt <span class="nb">install </span>cmake g++ gcc-arm-none-eabi doxygen libnewlib-arm-none-eabi git python3 build-essential
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Configure the environment:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"export PICO_TOOLCHAIN_PATH=..."</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.bashrc
<span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"export PICO_SDK_PATH=</span><span class="nv">$HOME</span><span class="s2">/micro_ros_ws/src/pico-sdk"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.bashrc
<span class="nb">source</span> ~/.bashrc
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="pico-sdk-and-microros">Pico-SDK and microROS</h2> <p>Create the workspace and clone the required repositories:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">mkdir</span> <span class="nt">-p</span> ~/micro_ros_ws/src
<span class="nb">cd</span> ~/micro_ros_ws/src
git clone <span class="nt">--recurse-submodules</span> https://github.com/raspberrypi/pico-sdk.git
git clone https://github.com/Rotvie/micro_ros_raspberrypi_pico_sdk.git
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="compilation-and-loading">Compilation and Loading</h2> <p>Compile the microROS code to generate the UF2 file, which will be loaded onto the Raspberry Pi Pico:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">cd </span>micro_ros_raspberrypi_pico_sdk
<span class="nb">mkdir </span>build
<span class="nb">cd </span>build
cmake ..
make
</code></pre></div></div> <p>To load the UF2 file, connect the Pico while holding the BOOTSEL button, then run:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">cp </span>build/pico_micro_ros_example.uf2 /media/<span class="nv">$USER</span>/RPI-RP2
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="configuring-the-microros-agent">Configuring the microROS agent</h2> <p>Install and configure the microROS agent:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>snap <span class="nb">install </span>micro-ros-agent
<span class="nb">sudo </span>snap <span class="nb">set </span>core experimental.hotplug<span class="o">=</span><span class="nb">true
sudo </span>systemctl restart snapd
snap interface serial-port
snap connect micro-ros-agent:serial-port snapd:pico
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="running-the-microros-example-demo">Running the microROS example demo</h2> <p>To start the microROS node, run:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>micro-ros-agent serial <span class="nt">--dev</span> /dev/ttyACM0 <span class="nv">baudrate</span><span class="o">=</span>115200
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Check the available topics with:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>ros2 topic list
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="connecting-the-pico-with-a-raspberry-pi-instead-of-a-pc">Connecting the Pico with a Raspberry Pi Instead of a PC</h2> <p>For a Raspberry Pi setup, follow the instructions up to the Configuring the microROS agent section. However, if you encounter an error when installing the micro-ros-agent with snap (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">error: snap "micro-ros-agent" is not available on stable for this architecture (arm64)</code>), follow these steps:</p> <ol> <li>Set up a new ROS 2 workspace for the microROS agent:</li> </ol> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">source</span> /opt/ros/<span class="nv">$ROS_DISTRO</span>/setup.bash
<span class="nb">mkdir </span>uros_ws <span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span> <span class="nb">cd </span>uros_ws
git clone <span class="nt">-b</span> <span class="nv">$ROS_DISTRO</span> https://github.com/micro-ROS/micro_ros_setup.git src/micro_ros_setup
rosdep update <span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span> rosdep <span class="nb">install</span> <span class="nt">--from-paths</span> src <span class="nt">--ignore-src</span> <span class="nt">-y</span>
colcon build
<span class="nb">source install</span>/local_setup.bash
</code></pre></div></div> <ol> <li>Build the microROS Agent manually:</li> </ol> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>ros2 run micro_ros_setup create_agent_ws.sh
ros2 run micro_ros_setup build_agent.sh
<span class="nb">source install</span>/local_setup.sh
</code></pre></div></div> <ol> <li>Start the microROS Agent:</li> </ol> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>ros2 run micro_ros_agent micro_ros_agent <span class="nt">--dev</span> /dev/ttyACM0 <span class="nv">baudrate</span><span class="o">=</span>115200
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ricardo Huaman</name></author><category term="ros,"/><category term="microROS,"/><category term="microcontroller,"/><category term="robotics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tutorial on how to get microROS and ROS2 working together]]></summary></entry></feed>